Hello, in this video, I'm going to speak
about how to write clean regular expressions.
People often add redundant things
into their regular expressions.
Let's have a look at some examples. A lot of
people use a limiting quantifier with the minimum
threshold set to "1" in order to match a single
occurrence of a character. In fact, if they use
this pattern they just match the same as
using this pattern. It means that this limiting
quantifier with the minimum threshold set to "1"
is actually redundant. We can always remove this.
If you want to match a string that
contains a single lowercase letter
you just use anchors on both ends of
this character class. Another example
is a pattern like this which is actually
matching "http" string, have a look.
And we can write this string like this
or like this. Note that this pattern with a
limiting quantifier looks less readable. A lot of
people use character classes in their patterns, for
example, a very simple one that matches "a", "b" or "c".
However, a lot of people
think that adding commas or pipes
does not matter. Well, character classes match
any characters that are listed inside them.
So, this pattern with pipes matches
"a", "b" or "c" or a pipe character.
You can easily see it here, in the test
strings. Or, if you use commas they will also be
matched. When you use character classes make sure
you are using at least two patterns inside it.
For example, if you want to match "a" or
"b" you use a character class. If you use
"a" inside a character class the character class
is redundant, all you need is just "a". So, when you
use "\d" to match a digit it makes no sense
to put it inside square brackets. In some regex
flavors it doesn't mean the same. It doesn't make
sense to put the "\d" inside brackets
because even if you wanted to write one or more
digits it is enough to write "\d+".
Another common regex construct that is overused
in patterns is groups. Remember that groups are
only necessary when we want to capture a part of
a pattern and then use it or access it in some way,
or when we want to quantify a group of patterns
or use an alternation. In other cases, we don't need
groups, so either remove unnecessary groups or turn
them into non-capturing groups. Now, let's have a
look at a specific regular expression that can be
greatly simplified. Here, we can simplify a lot of
things. First, character classes. Let's remove the
character classes around the patterns that only
match a single type of character. So, whitespaces
here, non-whitespaces here, and so on and so forth.
Now, we can also remove the quantifiers that
only match a single occurrence of a character.
Here, this limiting quantifier is redundant because
it only matches a single occurrence of this
group pattern. Also, we can see that
there is a non-capturing group here
that does nothing: there is no alternation
inside it, it's not quantified, that's why we
can safely remove the group here. The same
non-capturing group is not necessary here.
There are more ways to enhance this regular
expression pattern if we have exact requirements.
For example, we could match any char other than
round brackets between the two round brackets
and it would make this expression more efficient.
We could also use an optional non-capturing group
here making both whitespace and non-whitespace
patterns obligatory. Remember that you can always
check the regex explanation on the right, you
can check more tips on writing optimal regular
expressions in the "FURTHER LINKS" section,
and if you liked my video please click "Like"
and subscribe to my channel if you haven't done
it yet. Thank you for watching, and happy regexing.